Finding Aid for Professional Secretaries International, Huron Valley Chapter records
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Professional Secretaries International, Huron Valley Chapter records 1953-1982
Professional Secretaries International, Huron Valley Chapter
85358 Bk 2
Non-profit, non-sectarian organization whose purpose was to promote professionalism among secretaries. Files include administrative records relating to the activities of the organization; minutes, newsletters, and reports.
3 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection (Donor No. 6904 ) was donated March 14, 1983.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
The Professional Secretaries International was founded in 1942 under the name National Secretaries Association (NSA). The original name was not changed until 1983. On June 7, 1952 the Huron Valley Chapter of the NSA was installed. Approval of the establishment of the Michigan State organization followed in November of the same year.
The NSA was a non-profit, non-sectarian organization whose purpose was to promote professionalism among secretaries. A variety of means were adopted to achieve this end. The NSA sponsored competitions to recognize and reward excellence, including the annual Boss of the Year (BOTY) and Secretary of the Year (SOTY) contests. Each year it offered a number of workshops and seminars to enable secretaries to continue learning as they worked. The seminars covered a wide spectrum of topics from the psychology of human relations to the workings of the business world. Similarly, the NSA issued instructional pamphlets for secretaries.
A major program sponsored by the NSA was the Certified Professional Secretary course, which tested secretarial skills and graded participants accordingly. It was the aim of this program to set uniform professional standards on the national level.
Another function of the NSA was to oversee local branches of the Future Secretaries Association, an organization for high school girls. The NSA endeavored to instill its values in these young women as well as helping them to learn the necessary skills. The Huron Valley Chapter annually awarded fifty dollars to the most promising of these young women to help pay for their educations. It also provided opportunities to visit an actual office and observe secretaries at work.
The NSA was not a union. It did not address itself to employee grievances or the issues of salary and benefits. Instead the organization adopted a code of ethics that emphasized personal loyalty and cooperation.
Nor was membership automatic for any secretary who wished to join. Applications had to be approved by other members, based on the applicant's ability and recommendations from employers. Thus the NSA maintained its character as a professional organization rather than a union or social club.
The records of the Professional Secretaries International, Huron Valley Chapter, consist of three linear feet of organizational materials covering the years 1953-1982. The material as been organized and described in two series: Records and Newsletters. Notable file headings within the Records Series include History, Activities, Committees, Directories/Membership, Meetings and Minutes.
Although there is some material from the Michigan Division of the NSA, the bulk of the collection documents the functioning of a local branch. The minutes, reports, and especially the newsletters, provide a detailed picture of the administration and activities of this NSA chapter from its founding in 1952 until 1981.
Beyond the study of the organization itself, the collection would be useful for studies relating to white-collar workers, professional organizations, the workings of bureaucracies, and women's history. Also, since the collection encompasses the period of the late 1960's and early 1970's when feminism was becoming an important issue, the collection has potential importance for its documentation of the self-image of secretaries and their attitudes towards their work.
Although there is some material from the Michigan Division of the NSA, the bulk of the collection documents the functioning of a local branch. The minutes, reports, and especially the newsletters, provide a detailed picture of the administration and activities of this NSA chapter from its founding in 1952 until 1981.
Beyond the study of the organization itself, the collection would be useful for studies relating to white-collar workers, professional organizations, the workings of bureaucracies, and women's history. Also, since the collection encompasses the period of the late 1960's and early 1970's when feminism was becoming an important issue, the collection has potential importance for its documentation of the self-image of secretaries and their attitudes towards their work.
Subjects:
Secretaries.; Women--Michigan--Washtenaw County--Societies and clubs.
- Records
  - History
    The History folder contains the NSA charter founding the Huron Valley chapter, as well as two publications on the history of the Michigan division of the NSA. These histories are not narrative, but instead present the structure of the organization with lists of past officers, conferences, and workshops.
  - Activities (Box 1)
    Under Activities, the researcher will find information on the Boss of the Year Award, civic projects, the Leadership and Orientation Program, the Testimonial Luncheon, and the Twenty-fifth Anniversary celebration of the chapter.
    - Boss of the Year 1963-1972 (Box 1)
    - Civic Projects 1966 (Box 1)
    - Leadership and orientation Program 1967 (Box 1)
    - Testimonial Luncheon 1966 (Box 1)
    - Twenty-fifth Anniversary (Huron Valley Chapter) 1977 (Box 1)
    - Miscellanea (Box 1)
  - Awards (Box 1)
  - Clippings (Box 1)
  - Committees
    Committees consist of the Program Committee and the Scholarship Committee. The Program Committee includes lectures on various cultural topics; while the Scholarship Committee deals with awards given to high school girls who aspired to become secretaries. Some of this material has also been filed under Future Secretaries Association.
    - Program Committee (Box 1)
    - Scholarship Committee 1957-1968 (Box 1)
  - Conferences
    - Annual Conference 1953-1954 (Box 1)
    - Great Lakes District Conference
      - 1965-1968 (Box 1)
      - 1969-1974 (Box 1)
  - Directories/Membership 1967-1981 (Box 1)
    The folders under Directories/Membership include not only lists of members and officers, but also applications for membership and correspondence relating to potential members.
  - Future Secretaries Association
    Future Secretaries Association is divided into a General file and also folders of Chapters, Correspondence, and Scholarships. This group of materials documents the NSA's relationship to the junior organization.
    - General (Box 1)
    - Chapters
      - Cleary College (Box 1)
      - Washtenaw Community College (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Scholarships (Box 1)
  - Meetings, Michigan Division Annual
    - 1957 (Box 1)
    - 1965 (Box 1)
    - 1966 (Box 1)
    - 1967 (Box 1)
    - 1968 (Box 1)
    - 1970-1972 (Box 1)
  - Minutes, Huron Valley Chapter
    - 1963-1970 (Box 1)
    - 1974-June, 1976 (Box 1)
    - August 1976-June, 1978 (Box 1)
    - August, 1978-1980 (Box 1)
- Newsletters (by chapter)
  Newsletters make up a large part of the collection. Arranged alphabetically by the chapter which produced them, the collection includes newsletters for Detroit, Huron Valley, Jackson-Albion, the Michigan division, and River Park. Most, of course, are for the Huron Valley chapter. Entitled Valley News, this publication runs from 1953 to 1981. The first three years (1953-1956) have been bound in two volumes. The rest are in folders with only a few scattered gaps.
  - Detroit The Renaissance, 1980-1982 (Box 2)
  - Huron Valley Valley Views
    - January 1953-June, 1954 (Box 2)
    - July 1954-June, 1956 (Box 2)
    - September-December 1956 (Box 2)
    - January-April 1957 (Box 2)
    - May-October 1957 (Box 2)
    - November 1957-March 1958 (Box 2)
    - April-December 1958 (Box 2)
    - January-June 1959 (Box 2)
    - 1960 (Box 2)
    - 1961 (Box 2)
    - 1962 (Box 2)
    - 1963 (Box 2)
    - 1964 (Box 2)
    - 1965 (Box 2)
    - January-May, 1966 (Box 2)
    - June-December 1966 (Box 2)
    - 1967 (Box 2)
    - 1968 (Box 2)
    - 1969 (Box 2)
    - March 1972-December 1973 (Box 3)
    - 1974-1975 (Box 3)
    - January 1976-April 1977 (Box 3)
    - May-December 1977 (Box 3)
    - January-June, 1978 (Box 3)
    - September 1978-1979 (Box 3)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 3)
  - Jackson-Albion Jotter, 1981-1982 (Box 3)
  - Michigan Division The Flagship, 1972 (Box 3)
  - River Park Channel Notes, 1981-1982 (Box 3)
- Records
  - Reports 1963-1980 (Box 3)
  - Workshops/Seminars 1953-1980 (Box 3)
  - Miscellanea (Box 3)
  - Scrapbooks, 3 volumes (Box 3)